{
  "title": "Theory_of_Computation - Context_Free_Language — Slot 3 (19 Questions)",
  "duration": 53,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Context_Free_Language — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>The language \\(L=\\{0^{i}21^{i}|i\\geq 0\\}\\) over the alphabet {0,1,2} is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2007)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>not recursive</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>is recursive and is a deterministic CFL.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>is a regular language.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>is not a deterministic CFL but a CFL.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>is recursive and is a deterministic CFL.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1228/gate2007-30#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let L be a context-free language and M a regular language. Then the language \\(L \\cap M\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>always regular</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>never regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>always a deterministic context-free language</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>always a context-free language</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>always a context-free language</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3571/gate2006-it-32\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let  \\(L_{1}=\\{0^{n+m}1^{n}0^{m}|n,m\\geq 0\\}\\) <br> \\(L_{2}=\\{0^{n+m}1^{n+m}0^{m}|n,m\\geq 0\\}\\) <br> \\(L_{3}=\\{0^{n+m}1^{n+m}0^{n+m}|n,m\\geq 0\\}\\)<br> <br>Which of these languages are NOT context free? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L3 only</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L1 and L2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L2 and L3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>L2 and L3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/980/gate2006-19#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The language \\(\\{0^n 1^n 2^n \\mid 1 \\leq n \\leq 10^6\\}\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>regular</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>context-free but not regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>context-free but its complement is not context-free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>not context-free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>regular</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3751/gate2005-it-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Let L be a regular language and M be a context-free language, both over the alphabet \\(\\Sigma\\). Let \\(L^c\\) and \\(M^c\\) denote the complements of L and M respectively. Which of the following statements about the language  \\(L^c\\cup M^c\\) is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>It is necessarily regular but not necessarily context-free.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>It is necessarily context-free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>It is necessarily non-regular.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3748/gate2005-it-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Consider the languages: <br><br>\\(L_{1}=\\{ww^{R}|w\\in \\{0,1\\}*\\} \\) <br>\\( L_{2}=\\{w\\#w^{R}|w\\in \\{0,1\\}*\\}\\),where # is a special symbol  <br>\\(  L_{3}=\\{ww|w\\in \\{0,1\\}*\\}\\)<br> <br>Which one of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 is a deterministic CFL</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L2 is a deterministic CFL</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L3 is a CFL, but not a deterministic CFL</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L3 is a deterministic CFL</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>L2 is a deterministic CFL</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1380/gate2005-57#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Consider the languages: <br> \\(L_{1}=\\{a^{n}b^{n}c^{m}|n,m \\gt 0\\} \\) and \\(L_{2}=\\{a^{n}b^{m}c^{m}|n,m \\gt 0\\}\\)<br> Which one of the following statements is FALSE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\cap\\) L2 is a context-free language</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\cup\\) L2 is a context-free language</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L1 and L2 are context-free language</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\cap\\) L2 is a context sensitive language</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>L1 \\(\\cap\\) L2 is a context-free language</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1378/gate2005-55#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>The language {\\(a^{m}b^{n}c^{m+n}|m,n\\geq 1\\)} is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2004)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>regular</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>context-free but not regular</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>context sensitive but not context free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>type-0 but not context sensitive</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>context-free but not regular</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1081/gate2004-87#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>If the strings of a language L can be effectively enumerated in lexicographic (i.e.\nalphabetic) order, which of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2003)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L is necessarily finite</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L is regular but not necessarily finite</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L is context free but not necessarily regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L is recursive but not necessarily context free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>L is recursive but not necessarily context free</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/120/gate2003-15#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The C language is : <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2002)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A context free language</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A context sensitive language</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A regular language</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Parsable fully only by a Turing machine</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>A context sensitive language</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/848/gate2002-2-18#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Let L denote the languages generated by the grammar \\(S \\to 0S0 \\mid 00\\).\nWhich of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2000)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L = 0^+\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>L is regular but not \\(0^+\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>L is context free but not regular</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>L is not context free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>L is regular but not \\(0^+\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/628/gate2000-1-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>If L1 is context free language and L2 is a regular language which of the following is/are false? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>L1-L2 is not context free</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L1 \\cap L2\\) is context free</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\sim L1\\) is context free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\sim L2\\) is regular</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>L1-L2 is not context free</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1482/gate1999-2-4\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Context-free languages are closed under: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1999)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Union, intersection</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Union, Kleene closure</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Intersection, complement</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Complement, Kleene closure</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Union, Kleene closure</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1459/gate1999-1-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Define a context free languages \\(L \\in \\{0, 1\\}^*, \\text{init} (L) = \\{u \\mid uv \\in L\\) for some v in \\(\\{0, 1\\}^*\\}\\) ( in other words, \\(\\text{init}(L)\\) is the set of prefixes of L)<br>\nLet  \\(L = \\{w \\mid w \\text{ is nonempty and has an equal number of $0$'s and $1$'s}\\}\\)\nThen \\(\\text{init}(L)\\) is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>the set of all binary strings with unequal number of 0's and 1's</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>the set of all binary strings including null string</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>the set of all binary strings with exactly one more 0 than the number of 1's or one more 1 than the number of 0's</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>the set of all binary strings including null string</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2738/gate1996-2-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>If \\(L_1\\) and \\(L_2\\) are context free languages and R a regular set, one of the languages below is not necessarily a context free language. Which one? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(L_1.L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap L_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap R\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cup L_2\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(L_1 \\cap L_2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2737/gate1996-2-8\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 16,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following definitions below generate the same language as \\(L\\), where \\(L=\\{x^ny^n \\text{ such that } n\\geq 1 \\}\\)?<br>\nI.   \\(E \\rightarrow xEy\\mid xy\\)<br>\nII.  \\(x y \\mid (x^+xyy^+)\\)<br>\nIII. \\(x^+y^+\\)<br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I and II</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>II and III</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>II only</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>I only</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2632/gate1995-2-20\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 17,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements true ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>If a language is context free it can be always be accepted by a deterministic\npush-down automaton.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The union of two context free language is context free.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The intersection of two context free language is context free</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The complement of a context free language is context free</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>The union of two context free language is context free.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/698/gate2001-1-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 18,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only:<br>\nContext-free languages are: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1992)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>closed under union</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>closed under complementation</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>closed under intersection</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>closed under Kleene closure</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>closed under union</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/572/gate1992-02-xix\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 19,
          "question": "<p>Context-free languages and regular languages are both closed under the operation (s) of : <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1989)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Union</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Intersection</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Concatenation</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Complementation</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Union</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/87117/gate1989-3-ii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}